A Register of the Cherkasskii Family Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Cherkasskii Family Papers
1798-1974
75105
Cherkasskii family
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (2.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Cherkasskii family archives includes diaries, correspondence, writings, genealogy, books, clippings, printed matter, and photographs, relating to social conditions in Russia before the Russian Revolution, the Russian imperial army, the Russian Revolution and Civil War, Russian émigré affairs, and the Russian Orthodox Church abroad.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biography / Administrative History
The Cherkasskii family was prominent in the Russian government and the army from about 1500 until the very end of the seventeenth century. They were also the single richest boyar clan in Russia. From the end of the sixteenth century to Peter's time, they were the most important group of aristocrats of foreign origin at the court of the Russian tsars.
The Cherkasskis were clearly proud of their origins, evident from the section on the Circassian princes that appeared in the "Sovereign's genealogy", the quasi-official genealogy of the Russian aristocracy.
The papers cover the life of three generations of the Cherkasskii family: Prince Mikhail Alekseevich, born 1867, a civilian of high rank, who entered the guards officers lists. He joined the Kirasirs military Regiment and was in charge of a medical hospital, field hospitals, emergency, and first aid of the Kirasirs Regiment. Mikhail Alekseevich married Vera Pavlovna Likhacheva in 1892. They both died in 1953 in Brussels.
Their two sons Prince Aleksei Mikhailovich (1898-1920) and Prince Igor Mikhailoich (1895-1975) fought against the Bolsheviks during the Russian Civil War. The younger Prince Aleksei Mikhailovich, died in February 1920 fighting the Bolsheviks, and Prince Igor Mikhailovich, member of the corps of Pages, Lieutenant-Colonel lived long life and died in Brussels in 1975. He was married to Zoia Sergeevna Rodzianko (1901-1949) in 1921. Their daughter Princess Irina Igorevna has no heirs.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Cherkasskii family archives include diaries, correspondence, writings, genealogical materials, books, clippings, printed matter, and photographs, relating to social conditions in Russia before the Russian Revolution, the Russian imperial army, the Russian Revolution and Civil War, Russian émigré affairs, and the Russian Orthodox Church abroad.
The Cherkasskiis were clearly proud of their origin, evident from the section of the collection that appears in the genealogical charts. The collection also includes an official genealogy of the Russian aristocracy with the place of the Cherkaskii family prominent.
The Cherkasskii family papers consist of material related to the life and work of this prominent Russian family, both in Russia and abroad, from 1798 to 1974. The collection includes a wealth of biographical material found in the series related to the last three generations of the family. Of special interest is material from the period of the Russian Civil War, which includes a descriptive essay on Prince Aleksei Mikhailovich written by his brother. The biographical file further includes documentary material related to the Cherkasskii family life abroad and their exile to Belgium. Also interesting are materials related to family political activities, and participation in the life of the Russian Orthodox Church abroad.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 4 series: Cherkasskii family archives, Photographs, Subject file, and Printed matter
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
Russia. ArmiiaߞOfficers; Russia—Emigration and immigration; Russia—Court and courtiers; Soviet union-History-revolution, 1917-1921; Russkara pravoslavmaia tsrkov'; World War, 1914-1918; Diaries; Photographs
Related Material
Russian Subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Container List
- Cherkasskii family archives, 1798-1967. (Box 1)
  Arranged chronologically by age of the family member
  - Memoirs, 1883-1903 (Folder 1: 1)
    Holograph written by Princess Natalia Petrovna and continued by her daughter Princess Natalia Evgenievna Cherkasskii
  - Prince Mikhail Alekseevich Cherkasskii, 1867-1953, and Princess Vera Pavlovna Cherkasskaia (born Likhacheva)
    - Family coat of arms., See also oversize material for extended genealogical chart (Folder 1: 2)
      Includes photograph, description, and copy of the certificate issued by the governing senate of Russia on September 6, 1798, as well as Cherkasskii family genealogical survey.
    - Personal documents, 1920-1947. (Folder 1: 3)
      Includes passports, visa documents, and identity certificates from Belgium and the Dutch consulate in Constantinople
    - Biography, Mikhail Alekseevich Cherkasskii, 1965. (Folder 1: 4)
      Holograph written by his son Igor
    - Correspondence, 1918-1941. (Folder 1: 5)
      Includes military order for medal award to Prince Mikhail Alekseevich Cherkasskii, 1919
    - Career records from Graham Station Service (automobile business), Brussels, 1923-1948. (Folder 1: 6)
    - Russian Orthodox Church in Brussels and the Committee on the construction of the Russian Orthodox Cathedral-monument to the martyred Russian Tsar and other victims of Bolshevism, 1930-1950.; See also material from the second All International Congress of the Russian Orthodox Church abroad, Sremskie Karlovtsy, Yugoslavia, 1938. Printed copy (Folder 1: 7)
      Includes correspondence, newsletter, and photographs.
    - Greeting on the fiftieth wedding anniversary of Prince Mikhail Cherkasskii and Princess Vera Cherkasskii, 1892-1942. (Folder 1: 8)
      Includes photographs
    - Obituaries and letters of condolences on death of Mikhail and Vera Cherkasskii written to their son Igor, 1953. (Folder 1: 9)
  - Prince Aleksei Mikhailovich Cherkasskii, 1898-1920.
    (son)
    - Photographs (from the family album), 1898-1920. (Folder 1: 10)
    - Will, addressed to his brother Igor Cherkasskii, circa 1919-1920 (Folder 1: 11)
      (fallen in February 1920 at Bolshevik hands, Russian Civil War)
    - Necrology, written by Igor Cherkasskii on the death of his brother Aleksei, 1920. (Folder 1: 12)
  - Picture from the memorial plaque of Prince Aleksei Mikhailovich Cherkasskii in the Russian Orthodox Cathedral-monument in Brussels, Belgium, undated (Folder 1: 13)
  - Prince Igor Mikhailovich Cherkasskii (Corps des Pages, Stab-rotmister), 1895-1975, and Zoia Sergeevna Cherkasskii (born Rodzianko), 1901-1949.
    - Marriage certificate of Igor and Zoia Cherkasskii, 1921. (Folder 1: 14)
    - Personal documents, 1942; 1945. (Folder 1: 15)
      Includes letter of reference and work permit
    - Correspondence, 1946-1967. (Folder 1: 16)
    - Verses, undated. (Folder 1: 17)
- Photographs from the family album. (Folder 1: 18)
  Includes pictures of Mikhail and Vera Cherkasskii, Igor and Zoia Cherkasskii, and their daughter Princess Irina Igorevna Cherkasskii, as well as photographs from the funeral of the General Peter Vrangel, Commander of the Russian Army in exile. Arranged by the family
- Subject file, 1866-1920.
  Arranged alphabetically
  - Memoirs, Lagodovskii B. A., 1918-1920. (Folder 1: 19)
  - Personal papers, Baron Vrangel Kiril Konstantinovich, 1909-1917. (Folder 1: 20)
    Includes passport, visa, certificate of award, and appeal
  - Russian Imperial bonds, 1866. (Folder 1: 21)
- Printed matter, 1884-1974.
  Arranged chronologically
  - Leroy-Beaulieu, Anatole, Un homme d'État russe (Nicolas Milutine) d'après sa correspondance inédite; étude sur la Russie et la Pologne pendant le règne d'Alexandre II (1855-1872), Paris, Hachette et cie, 1884. (Folder 1: 22)
  - Deianiia Vtorogo Vsezarubezhnogo Sobora Russkoi Pravoslavoi TSerkvi Zagranitsei, s uchastiem predstavitelei klira i mirian, sostoisvshegosia 1/14-11/24 avgusta 1938 goda v Sremskikh Karlovitsakh v IUgoslavii(Minutes of meetings of the Second All International Congress of the Russian Orthodox Church abroad, Sremskie Karlovtsy, Yugoslavia, 1938), Belgrade, 1939. (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Pouchkine, N. de, Armorial de la Noblesse de Russie, armoiries des Familles resident en Belgique, Brussels, 1940. (Folder 2: 2)
  - Pashennyi, Nikolai, Imperatorskoe uchilishche pravovedeniia i pravovedy v gody mira, voiny i smuty(Imperial law college during years of peace, war, and unrest), Madrid, 1967. (Folder 2: 3)
  - Voennaia Byl' (Le Passé Militaire), military bulletin of the all cadet union, Paris, 1973; 1974 (Folder 2: 4)
- Two oversize Cherkasskii family genealogical charts, undated. (Box 3)